<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Newes out of the east, of the common enemy, who is yet in being in Hungaria and Austria. Or, a true account of the tryals and sufferings, jeopardies and tortourings, which Iohn Philly and William Moore passed through of late in the aforesaid countries</title>
            <author>Caton, William, 1636-1665.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 60KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B28104</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99828404</idno>
  <idno type="VID">206905</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240883435</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing P2128</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99828404</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99828404e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B28104)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 206905)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1857:04)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Newes out of the east, of the common enemy, who is yet in being in Hungaria and Austria. Or, a true account of the tryals and sufferings, jeopardies and tortourings, which Iohn Philly and William Moore passed through of late in the aforesaid countries</title>
                  <author>Caton, William, 1636-1665.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year 1664.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Preface signed: W.C. [i.e. William Caton].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Philly, John.</term>
               <term type="personal_name">Moore, William, --  of the Society of Friends.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Society of Friends --  Apologetic works --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Missionaries --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:206905:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:206905:1"/>
            <p> NEWES Out of the EAST, Of the common Enemy, who is yet in being in <hi>Hungaria</hi> and <hi>Austria.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Or, A true ACCOUNT Of the Tryals and Sufferings, Jeopardies and Tortourings, which <hi>Iohn Philly</hi> and <hi>William Moore</hi> passed through of late in the aforesaid Countries.</p>
            <p>Printed in the year 1664.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:206905:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:206905:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THis following Account coming to my hands, of the Travells and sufferings of the aforesaid Brethren, I could not well omit to communicate the same to the body of Friends; and how to make it most publick, I knew not better then in the first place to commit it to the Presse, to the end that both they that are nigh and they that are afar off may see and understand what the aforesaid brethren have so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>journed through in foreign Parts among the <hi>Catholicks</hi> (so called) and how that distructive spirit of persecution, and common enemy to peace and tranquility is yet found residing among them, as friends have found by sad experience, not only at <hi>Rome, Paris, Malta,</hi> and elsewhere to the Southward, but now finally in <hi>Hungaria</hi> and <hi>Austria,</hi> to the Eastward; And what temptations and provocations our friends have had from that Generation, is now become evident to many; yet thanks be to God, who through the arm of his power hath hitherto pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served them out of their snare; and they have chosen rather to suffer their torments and torturings (which they have been suffered to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flict upon them) then to imbrace their pleasures and proffers of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment, whereby they have manifested themselves to be of the true Israelites indeed, and to be minded like <hi>Moses, who chused rather to suffer affliction with the people of God, then to enjoy the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sures of sin for a season.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Surely, many shall be made to confesse, that of a truth God is with this people; and that it is for righteousnesse sake that they suffer, whose sufferings are thus great, sometimes by the <hi>Catholicks</hi> (so called) in their Dominions (as appears from this following Narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) and sometimes by the <hi>Lutherans</hi> in their Dominions; as at <hi>Hamborough</hi> (where they cast some of them into prison, and put irons upon them, and spoiled their goods, and finally banished them) and at <hi>Danzick,</hi> where they imprisoned and banished them, besides what they have suffered by them in <hi>Denmark,</hi> and in some part of <hi>Germany,</hi> And how have they suffered by the <hi>Calvinists</hi> in the Low Countries, and in the <hi>Palatinate</hi> in <hi>Germany?</hi> as also by the ridged <hi>Presbyterians</hi> in <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> and especially by the blood-thirsty and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postatized <hi>Professours</hi> of <hi>New-England,</hi> whose height of cruelty extend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the taking away of some of their lives: have we not also seen their great sufferings by the degenerated <hi>Independants,</hi> when they had
<pb facs="tcp:206905:3"/> assumed Authority to be as Lords in matters Civil and Ecclesiastical? And now finally do we see their daily sufferings by such as with a high hand rule over them: and who is there that considereth these things, or truly layeth them to heart? surely, surely, because of the oppressions and cruelties which are found among them that professe themselves to be Christians, but are not like Christ: the Land shall mourn, and the inhabitants thereof shall be afflicted; for behold the Lord hath seen the evil which hath been found among all the sorts of people before mentioned, and his very soul doth lothe the same, and his indignation is against that relix of <hi>Cain</hi>'s and <hi>Haman</hi>'s spirit which at this day is to be found among the many sorts of people before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned; and he is determined to arise to ease himself of his enemies, &amp; to avenge himself of his adversaries, and he will plead the cause of his people, who hath all power in his hand, and is able to bring to passe whatsoever he will; To him be glory and dominion world with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out end.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>W. C.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Yarmouth,</hi>
                  <date>the 15. of the 12. moneth, 1663.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:206905:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>An Account to</hi> William Caton <hi>and the rest of his fellow Prisoners, or to any of the true Christiane, of the remarkablest Sufferings and tryals, jeopardies and torments, which</hi> John Philly <hi>and</hi> William Moore <hi>went through in</hi> Hungaria <hi>and</hi> Austria, <hi>from the first moneth</hi> Anno 1662. <hi>untill the seventh moneth</hi> 1663. <hi>Together with their deliverances.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THe 29. of the 1. moneth (called <hi>March)</hi> 1662. <hi>John Philly</hi> &amp; I▪ <hi>William Moore</hi> being refreshed by the overflowing of the streams of the love of God through thee, we took our leave of thee and the rest of our dear friends in <hi>Germany,</hi> and what a crosse it was to my flesh and bloud to leave thee and them, and to take such an unknown Journey, its best known to him that seeth the secrets of all hearts, and what a capasity I was in, is pretty well known to thy self; yet we passed according to the information thou hadst procured for us of the way, together with what we got elsewhere, and we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spered in our Journey, and arrived the 16. of the 2. moneth at <hi>Cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>short</hi> by the <hi>Hottersche Brethren</hi> about a dayes journey from <hi>Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg</hi> in <hi>Hungaria,</hi> where we were pretty kindly entertained by some of them, and there I dealt some of the Books among them which I had carried along with me, and the next day I went alone to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Family of them, (Note they were a kind of <hi>Baptists</hi> which dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered from others, in having their goods common, neither would they swear, nor fight with carnal weapon, and lived by hundreds together as one Family) And in my going thither the Lord preserved me out of the hands of a wicked man which I met withall, who seeing me a stranger, would (its like) have laid violent hands on me, or have knockt me on the head for my mony, had not the Lord restrained him; and the Brethren (so called) wondered I was preserved, for they could not goe so far as to the next Village, but were in danger; and when we had had some pretty good service among them, we got the names of some more of their Families, and one of them was 300. miles farther at a City called <hi>Pattock</hi> in upper <hi>Hungaria,</hi> but some of them would have disswaded us from going any farther, but rather on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to have visitred the Families thereabouts, which I could have been free unto, but <hi>John</hi> was pressed to goe forwards, and I had not free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to leave him, he not having their Language, which I had.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:206905:4"/>
            <p> After that we returned to <hi>Presburg</hi> where the <hi>Donow</hi> devided it self, and it meets at <hi>Comora</hi> where we were taken, which happened as followeth; we finding a Boat going with Meale to the Garrison at <hi>New-hausell,</hi> which lies in the way to <hi>Pattock,</hi> we went along in her, and when we came near unto the place, the Boat-men asked me whether I had acquaintance there, I said no; or whether we had a Pass, I said no; then said they it is dangerous going thither, because they would be suspitious of us; and to travel further in that Land, they being Tributaries to the <hi>Turk,</hi> we should be in danger of being killed either by the Countrey men, or by some of the <hi>Turks;</hi> and at that Garrison they did use to put men to cruell deaths which have been found without leave on the Tributary ground, yet <hi>John</hi> was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sirous to be at that Village which was near there, but said the Boat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, he will not take counsell before ye shall remember our words, and repent it when you cannot help it, &amp;c. and their words had the more impression upon me, because I had seen a night or two before in my sleep, that which afterwards came to passe at <hi>Comora,</hi> where we arrived, and were brought into an <hi>Hungarians</hi> Lodging but could not understand one another, but the next night they sent for a Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent from the Colledge who asked me in <hi>Latine,</hi> whence we were, and whither we intended? I told him we came from <hi>Great Britain,</hi> and desired to be at <hi>Pattock,</hi> afterwards we entered into discourse a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Religion, and when we parted, he said he wished us well, though there was a vast difference in our judgement, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next day we endeavoured to get over the River, and made signes to a Countrey man with some money, who began to make his Boat ready to help us; but an old <hi>Dutch</hi> woman came forth, and said, <hi>what doe ye?</hi> and told me the Governour will presently cause him to be hanged, if he set us over; so we let it rest, and returned to our former Lodging: and the next day I went over the water on the South<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>side of the Town, where I heard there were many <hi>Dutch</hi> people and Souldiers, hoping to find some Countrey men to speak with, and some Books I took with me which I would willingly have sent to <hi>Pattock,</hi> and coming by the Souldiers, asked for Countrey men, but finding none, I asked leave of the Guard, and walked out into the field, where a Trooper sat Centinel, discoursed a little with him, and passed on farther where some were a Plowing, and as I returned back there did meet me a Souldier of Captain <hi>Fuchses</hi> Company with two
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:206905:4"/> other, and having a Book in my hand called <hi>A Paper sent forth into the world, to shew the ground and reasons why we denied the Priests of the World;</hi> he looked on the Title, and began voluntarily to tell me, that such a place was in <hi>Turky,</hi> and if a man went thither he might have good daies there, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but I said, I will goe from whence I came, and intending to return to <hi>John</hi> to the other side of the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter again, the aforesaid Souldier came to me again at the water side, and told me I must come to the Captain, and when I came before him, he asked for the Book, and looking on it, asked if I was a <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker,</hi> I said yea, and he being in a rage, said, <hi>These Rogues shew no respect,</hi> and said I was a young <hi>John Hus</hi> come forth to seduce people and make uproars, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and he caused the Souldiers to pull off my clothes, and search me for Letters, and take my money from me, and I spake something to them to give them to understand that they would not be so done by, but he said, when you get clear you shall have your money again, but he did not think that that should be, so he sent me to the Guard a while, and sent for me again and searched me more narrowly, and found the Books which were inclosed between the Lynings and my Breeches, then was I sent to the Guard a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, and the Marshal was to put Iron Shackles with a Chain upon my foot and hand, and there was a talk as if I should in a short time be stuck upon a wooden Spit, as some have been who had but gone to the next Village without their order, but I turned my mind inward, and was pretty well resigned up to the Lord: so they having sent over to the chiefe Officer to inform him, there were Souldiers sent with their burning matches to fetch me, and I little expecting lesse then present death had told some Souldiers, I had a Companion in the Inn on the other side, and he would marvel what was become of me if he did not hear; afterwards I was carried to the aforesaid Officer, who asked me, <hi>if</hi> Mary <hi>had continued alwaies a Virgin?</hi> to which when I had an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered, <hi>thou Rogue</hi> (said he) <hi>if I had but power over thee, I would pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sently drown thee in this water;</hi> afterwards they went to our Lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and apprehended <hi>John</hi> also, howbeit free of that crime which they imputed to me, which was for going over, and in the Garrison I was put in the <hi>Dutch</hi> Prison called the <hi>Stock-house,</hi> and <hi>John</hi> into the <hi>Hungarians</hi> Vault which was twenty foot long, where they wrack people, and there was a private Gallows, a pair of Stocks, and a filthy tub of Excrements; and the the aforesaid Officer took our
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:206905:5"/> Port-mantle, but afterwards it was given to the Marshal, who took what pleased him out of it with the Bible and Papers, and left the rest to another Officer, who feignedly after our commitment seemed to be troubled that we had no bread, and asked me whether <hi>John</hi> had not some money, which I could not deny, and then he went to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Prison and threatned him to give it him, so <hi>John</hi> gave him a Duccate, which he got changed and brought us the money, and desired we would give him some of it, and he would be worth it at our hands; <hi>John</hi> afterward<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> expecting they would search him for Gold, did afterwards hide some, and kept some by him.</p>
            <p>The day following we were first examined by the Inquisitor, whence we were? whither we intended? &amp; how old we were? and who was the Authour of our coming forth? what money we had taken up? and <hi>John</hi> was searched and the Gold found which he had left by him; and I was examined concerning the Books, and told it was a Capital Crime, and it would cost my life, but I said what I had done there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, I had done it in simplicity, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and he asked who had spoke with us in our Lodging, I told him a Student; with many more words.</p>
            <p>And after the first examination one Collonel <hi>Fuchs,</hi> desired to have me brought forth before him, and he asked me several questions concerning the Books, and who was the first bringer up of this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine? I told him <hi>George Fox</hi> was one of the first Preachers of it in this Generation, and because I owned the Books aforesaid to be written by the motion of the spirit of God, he was very bitter against me, and several cunning questions he did ask me, as thereby to ensnare me, but it did not avail; something he read in one of the Books con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning their Steeple-houses, as advice to people that they should goe no more to them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which seemed to be very odious to him, and he told one how he caused or would cause all them Books and writings to be Copyed and sent to his Prince at <hi>Mentz,</hi> and when he could spare them the Inquisitor should have them. Afterwards I was taken to the Deputy Governour a (cruell old Fox) who asked me several Questions, &amp; said he would send me with a Message to the Devil, and he said I had done worse then if I had killed a hundred men; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause I would not take of my hat, he judged that to be a <hi>Turkish</hi> principle; and I not being free at that time to drink wine, he asked me why? I said because I would bring my body into subjection; how long (said he) will you abstain? I said till night at least; that, said
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:206905:5"/> he, is another <hi>Turkish</hi> point, to fast till night: he had also sent for the <hi>Hungarian</hi> student, and commanded him to tell him in Latine all what had passed between us in our Lodging, which the Inquisitour afterwards took to read when we were examined; but he would not read it openly, le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>st the sitters by should have heard, and owned the Truth thereof. Afterwards they brought our attempting to go over the water as a mighty crime against us, and the aforesaid souldier was called to testifie against me, whose Testimony being false, I withstood him, and told the Inquisitour (who did much seek an occasion against me) that he should beware what he did, for if he should cause my Bloud to be shed under such a pretence, it would cry to the Lord for Vengeance, and thereby he might draw the wrath of God upon him and others. And I desired the other souldiers might be examined, who also had heard what I had said, which after some time was granted, and I was put forth, and my Adversary and accuser he was kept within, and one of the other was called: And then I thought, <hi>Now if the Lord do not assist me, they may perswade him to speak the same thing;</hi> but when he came forth, he told me he did not speak as the other, for that which the other had affirmed was not true; then I thanked the Lord that this pretence failed them.</p>
            <p>But afterwards the Inquisitour told me, the Books were enough, though there were nothing else, and asked me whether I knew not, that the Catholicks had Lawes to burn and torment Hereticks, and such as carried such Books. I said, I should not have expected such Dealing among good Christians, and so did not tell him, howbeit I knew well, that they were Cruel and bloudie enough.</p>
            <p>Then he opened a book of the corrupt Popish Lawes, and read therein, how that such persons as do carry such Books &amp; papers are to be racked, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And about this time was <hi>John</hi> searched yet further for Gold by the command of the Inquisitour, and having taken off so far as one of his shoes and stockings, he was slow in taking off that where the Gold was, and the Marshal thinking it tedious, and thinking there had been no more, bid him put them on again, and upon a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain time he gave it me, in half a little white loaf when we stood with the souldiers waiting to be called.—And they seeing the Book cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>The way to the Kingdome,</hi> that it was printed at <hi>Amsterdam,</hi> asked me what Books I brought from thence to the <hi>Palz,</hi> and how many, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and one morning having sent for one of the Priests, he got that writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:206905:6"/> Book of <hi>G. Foxes</hi> of the Apostacie of Christendome, who look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on it, begun to be hot and wrathfull, saying, How are we (mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Papists) Apostatized? and how could that be proved? I said, Friend, it becometh not a spiritual man to be so furious, but gentle, meek, peaceable, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> then was his countenance dashed, and had little more to say. The Inquisitour asked me further concerning the Sacraments, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And I told him how Christ said, <hi>the Flesh profited little, it was the Spirit which quickned,</hi> &amp;c. which seemed strange to him, and he asked the Priest, Sir Father how is that? who bethought himself, and said he did remember there was such a saying, and more words passed between us, which would be now too long to relate: fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Inquisitour asked me, if I would be a <hi>Catholick?</hi> I said if I should be so for fear or favour of them, the Lord not requiring it of me, I should not have peace in my Conscience, and the displeasure of the Lord would be more intolerable then theirs. And as for compelling people, that did but make them Hypocrites, and doth not truly change the heart; which the Priest could not deny but that it was true. And notwithstanding our Innocencie, we heard the Governour would have us <hi>Racked,</hi> which seemed to me according to relation to be a cruel Torment; and in these dayes I often poured forth my supplications unto the Lord with teares: And being almost every day examined till the eighth day, they made ready Benches to sit on, lighted the Candle, and put <hi>John</hi> out of his room, and sent for me, and the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quisitour sitting there with two more Officers, and the Marshal and Hangman by them. The Inquisitour said, <hi>William,</hi> that you may not think that we will deal with you as Tyrants, we will lay it before you, that you may tell what you know in time, for if you be Racked you will be but a miserable man, and must have your head cut of besides, but I told him I know no evil, nor had had no such thing in my heart against them; then did he read a few lines to this purpose, <hi>We</hi> Leo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poldus, &amp;c. <hi>Emperour of,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>having understoood of two suspected persons,</hi> John Philly <hi>and</hi> William Moor, <hi>found by our frontier Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>risons, our desire is they should be Racked to know their Intent.</hi> And then the Hangman according to order put an Iron Skrew hard on my Thumbs, and bid me, <hi>Tell out;</hi> then slacked them, and skrewed them harder again, but that not availing, he was commanded to proceed further, and so he tyed a small Cord about my Wrists behind my back, and drew me up some degrees on the Ladder, and tyed my hands
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:206905:6"/> to one of them, and another Cord about the Ancles of of my Legs, and with a big battle of wood between my feet, lifted up my body quite from the Ladder, and at the first pull my left Arm gave a pretty loud crack out of joint, being shorter tied above that wrist-bone: then he was bid put it in joint again, so he slacked; and they asked me (having three things especially to ask) 1. why I did ask the Student, If one should come to them, and say he intended to buy somewhat of them, If they would then kill him? 2. Why we had desired to be set over the water at the Town, and who was the Authour? 3. Why had I written up some of the names of their Garrisons and other places notwithstanding I had them in the Map?</p>
            <p>And though he mentioned but three questions at the first, yet he would have forced me to have told wheth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>r <hi>J. Philly</hi> was an Ingenier, a Gunner, or a Minister? Now this suspition of being a Minister, had an <hi>Irish</hi> man (it seems) put in their heads, who had almost an irrecon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cileable hatred or malice in him against <hi>English</hi> men, as I after out of his own mouth plainly unde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>stood, especially against Ministers, as Authours of their ruine and exile, and this man was Interpreter between him and them; but I answered and kept to this that he was a Husband-man and Malt-Man, and I knew him not till he came to <hi>Amsterdam,</hi> &amp;c. He asked me if I had a mind to goe to the <hi>Turk</hi> and to be one? I said I had rather die then be one; in the mean time I was so wracked, that my chin went so close to my breast and closed my mouth, that I was almost choaked, and could not well speak any longer; and I should not wish any to experience how painfull it was, and yet they would be questioning of me; then I asked them, where is now the Christian love? and do you now do as you would be done unto? and I cryed the louder that them people that were without might hear &amp; bear witness what they were a doing to me, for the door was shut and guarded, and sometimes when I was slacked, it was almost as painfull as the pulling, but something they would have out of me, and I told them how that they might by such means force one (as I believed many had been) to say more then they knew, to be put out of pain, for I had rather they had proceeded to have beheaded me, according to their threatnings, then so to have tormented me, but yet that they would not do then, for he said they would have me say yea to it, which (its like) would have been enough to them, though they had known us to have confessed a Lye, howbeit finally
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:206905:7"/>
               <hi>I</hi> confessed, <hi>It was for love to our Religion that we were come to them places;</hi> then they left off thinking there was crime enough, yet he spoke as if I should be wracked again on the third day.</p>
            <p>Then they fetcht <hi>John,</hi> who not seeing me, but hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng heard me crying out before, he thought I had been hanged on the private Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, and put out of the way, but he was given up, being confident in the Lord who had sealed to him (he said) he should have his life for a prey before he came forth, so they laid four things before him chiefly to answer, &amp; his thumbs were skrewed, &amp; he was drawn on the Ladder twice, &amp; he cryed <hi>Innocent,</hi> &amp; asking the Interpreter what that was, he said they were smitten in their consciences, and they left off, I judge the sooner, because if there had been any evil they would have got it out of me, with whom they had more delight to meddle, being they could understand me &amp; I them, &amp; then it was afternoon, &amp; they hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry (its like) for they had begun early with me; &amp; when all was done. and they could find no contradiction, they invented a lye, and the Marshal came to me, and said, <hi>John</hi> had said, I have no money by me but what was his, and bid me tell how it was, which I knew to be otherwise, but they sought occasion against us that they might yet have tormented us more, but I kept to truth, which he also had spoken, and their expectation failed them.</p>
            <p>Afterwards a Priest with the Marshal came and felt my ears, to see whether I had been a Rogue, or some one of account, which they would have concluded if they had been either cut or bored.</p>
            <p>When all this had passed, they told me there would be 24, or 30. men of Note appointed out of the Quarters round about, to hold a Court of Justice upon us, and to determine what death we should die, and to make new Lawes for our sakes, but in the mean time the Inquisitor came and would have me first write some of the heads of my Religion, so I did write many particulars which I cannot now set down word by word, at some of which he raged very much.</p>
            <p>About that time <hi>J. Philly</hi> feeling much of the wickednesse of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quisitour and Priests, and being sensible how they plotted to take away our lives, did once cry out to the Governour when he was in his Coach, and he sent to know what he would, which was to acquaint him with those particulars laid before him in his wracking, and what his answers were, and how that there was no contradiction
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:206905:7"/> found in our Answers, for he was jealous that the Inquisitour and Priests would pervert our words to the Governour; and afterwards he got pen and ink and wrote to the Governour, but afterwards the Inquisitour got it, and sought to keep it from the Governour, for it's like he was convicted in his Conscience of his his dealing so evilly with us; but <hi>John</hi> perceiving he would smother it, called to the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour again, who commanded him to give me it to translate for him, which was done; so not long after came the Inquisitour to me having been sick three dayes upon his bed, and told me he was sent by the Governour, that we might go forth and fill a little earth in the wheel-barrowes with the Slaves, whereby we might earn near two pence a day to buy us Bread, for said he, that which remains in my hands of the money is little for my pains, and the Marshal and Hangman will have some for their pains. This was about five weeks after our coming to <hi>Comora.</hi> And we were willing to accept of the Governour's proffer, that we might thereby have the benefit of the fresh air, and that our bonds might be manifest to such as might some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what take it to heart: For there were both <hi>Lutherans</hi> and <hi>Calvinists,</hi> who partly did commiserate our condition, but durst not venture to come to see us in the Castle, and sometimes was some small thing gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven us by some, and the <hi>Papists</hi> marvelled, and others were glad we had obtained the favour as to be suffered to work; yet sometimes the Marshal would not suffer us to go out, and sometimes he kept back of our Wages; and on Saints dayes (so called) and on rainy dayes we had no Wages, howbeit the Lord provided for us; for there were some Women that remembred us on them dayes, and pretty much we could have gotten if we had spoken to rich people and Officers, but we were not free to beg of any, whereupon the Marshal was angry: and as for that Gold which <hi>John</hi> had hid in the Prison wall, some had found it, and taken it away. And when we had been about seven weeks asunder, <hi>John</hi> obtained that favour as to be with me, but one night he was in danger of being Murthered by a Student, who pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vately got to him when he was asleep, and got him by the neck, and might have choaked him, had not the Lord prevented him.</p>
            <p>After that <hi>John</hi> wrote again to the Governour, and commended his wisdome in forbearing to proceed so severely against us, as some would gladly have had him, but that paper the Inquisitour did also in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible: left margin cropped or obscured" resp="#murp" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ercept, and he sent for me, and threatned how he would now help us
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:206905:8"/> to the Gallows himself, howbeit I have spared and helped you before said he; and about that time I did eat little, that I might be the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter prepared for to die the sooner, if they should have been suffered to have hung me upon a Hook by the Ribbs, as it was their manner with some, who lived in a most miserable pain for three or four dayes.</p>
            <p>After that I wrote something to the Governour, but the Inquisi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour did also intercept that, and I spoke with the Governour's Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary and with his Chamberlain, who were two pretty discreet young men; and one of them told me how the Inquisitour was made to give his lord our Papers which he had intercepted, and it appeared to us that he was come in disfavour with the Governour, and the Chief Priest (our great Adversary) was in danger of being punished, but for what cause we did not certainly know; however that evening the Chain was taken off each of us, and but a little left upon one Leg.</p>
            <p>After that came down the General President with the Deputie Chancellour of the Empire and others to view the Garrison, and they came riding by us where we were at work, and one looking out of the Coach, and seeing us not take off our Hats, cryed saying, <hi>These are the Quakers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the same day was a new Gallows made, and we were called in, and by the way the Marshal said, we were to go before a General, and if we did not take off our hats, we should see what would become of us, for the Gallows was ready.</p>
            <p>And coming before them, there sate a Priest at the Table, who said we had forfeited our lives, by desiring to get over the River, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But I told him, they thirsted after bloud, and the Potentates of the earth harkned unto them; and as for us, we had no man, but God to plead for us: and many Sophistical Arguments he produced, as there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to ensnare me: but some of the rest desiring to speak with me, I regarded what he said the less, and with much boldness I spake unto them. And as for the President, who seemed to be the wisest amongst them, he called <hi>John</hi> to him, and spake <hi>French</hi> with him, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards called me and spake with me. The Deputy Chancellour asked me whether I would rather turn Papist, or be hanged? I said I did not desire to have them put it to my choice. The President asked me whether I would not that all people were as I was? I answered and said, Whatsoever was good in me, I wish them like me in that: But whether I would not they were all of my Religion? I said I wished
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:206905:8"/> that all might be faithfull to that which they knew already to be good: then he caused them to bring us our Hats again, which some had thrown off. And when they had dined, they desired us to write for Certifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cates, and so went their way.</p>
            <p>And upon a certain time Colonel <hi>Fusch</hi> came riding by (where we were at work) and some <hi>Italian</hi> lords with him, who were intended for <hi>Rome,</hi> and he proffered to send me with them if I pleased, or if I would be a <hi>Papist</hi> or <hi>Calvinist</hi> (i. e. <hi>Presbyterian,)</hi> he would procure my Liberty, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and many more temptations we had daily, which would be too long here to relate. And often there came Officers and asked us, <hi>What saith the Spirit now? hath the Spirit set you at work?</hi> and, <hi>had he not done better to have counselled you to have stayed at home?</hi> and, <hi>doth he not yet tell you, that you must be Catholicks?</hi> &amp;c. and when I had spoken to them, and they not knowing how to defend themselves, then they would say, <hi>Such Hereticks ought to be burned,</hi> with more bad wicked words to the same purpose.</p>
            <p>And when 16. weeks were expired of our imprisonment the <hi>Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garian</hi> Deputie Governour (a bitter old man) came where we were at work and said he must send us to <hi>Caesar,</hi> for <hi>John</hi> had before in his Paper appealed to him.</p>
            <p>Then we went into the Garrison untill four Souldiers, &amp; an Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preter and Letters were ready that went along with us, and there were Iron Boults put on our feet, and we put in a Wagon. And the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quisitor told us how he had heard the Letter which was come con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning us, but neverthelesse he said we should not come into <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land;</hi> so that whole night we rid, and arrived the third day at the house of one called His Excellency Earl <hi>Francis</hi> of <hi>Nadasti,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dex Curiae Hungariae,</hi> the Emperours Majesties active Privie Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sellour, and Lord Chamberlain, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> To whom the Governour of <hi>Comora</hi> had given us over, it was supposed partly to make friendship with him, for they had been formerly at variance; and when he came from his worship he caused us to be called; and he asked me if we were <hi>Quakers?</hi> I said yea; he said very well, very well; and in the afternoon his Wife looked out at a window, and called to me, and asked me several questions, and I had much freedome to answer her, which she interpreted to some <hi>Hungarians</hi> that were with her; and the next morning we were taken to the Vice King's Parlour, where the Lords of that Kingdome and of other Dominions were set
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:206905:9"/> about the Table, and <hi>John</hi> was ordered to goe to one end by the Secretary, who seemed to be an understanding man, and he was partly reached by <hi>John</hi>'s answer, and he was forward to repeat them aloud to the Arch-Bishop and the rest; and <hi>Nadasty</hi> asked me severel questions (but hastily) about our Religion, of which we gave friends an account formerly.</p>
            <p>And though they had little or nothing to say against our Answers, yet they passed the sentence on us, <hi>that we should be burned if we would not be instructed, and imbrace their Religion,</hi> for they had a Law (said they) which tolerated but three Religions, <hi>viz. Theirs,</hi> the <hi>Lutherans,</hi> and the <hi>Calvinists,</hi> and whosoever brought a new Religion there, was (according to their Law) to be burned, if he did not turn, and upon that we were sent away; and <hi>John</hi> told me, the power of the Lord would divide them in their Counsel, as an <hi>Irish</hi> Priest did afterwards tell him, who was sent to require an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of our Religion in writing; and when it was done, the <hi>Irish</hi> man got an <hi>English</hi> Copy of it, and said he would tell them the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents thereof, and help us what he could: but we thought it would be the best that I translated it, which accordingly I did, and <hi>John</hi> gave it <hi>Nadasty</hi> in his hand.</p>
            <p>Afterwards they sent the Priests to Convert us, and there he read out of his Catechism, and asked <hi>John</hi> concerning the <hi>Creed, Pater<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noster, Seven Sacraments, Mass, Faith, Hope, Love, Patience,</hi> and more such like things; to which <hi>John</hi> answered him, (which is to be seen in <hi>John</hi>'s Memorial, if it be to be had.) After that came some Priests and asked us, If we were come forth to sow our seed? Oh, said the <hi>Irish</hi> Priest, they cannot speak <hi>Latine,</hi> yet he and others knew that I could. And seeing they could not prevail with us there, we were sent to another place five <hi>Dutch</hi> miles from <hi>Wien</hi> (the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour's Seat) with two Souldiers by <hi>Nadastie</hi>'s command, and when we were come thither, the Priests gave order to put us in the Hole with the <hi>Turks,</hi> because they suspected us to be Preachers; and by their instigation, and with consent of the Court-Master (who told me that there should be Wood and Straw fetcht to burn us) did the Souldiers take off our Coats, and searched our Pockets, and took our Books and Papers: and the next day, because we would not speak <hi>Latine,</hi> nor take off our Hats to their Images in their Church (so cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led,) they set others upon us to ensnare us in words, and strove to
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:206905:9"/> do it themselves, that they might have occasion to take away our lives, which they often threatned to do; and when they could not prevail with all their cunning baits, nor make us bow to their Worship, they mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fested their cruelty further in causing Iron Shackles to be put upon our Hands, and though they were so little, that I was even forced to cry out by reason of the extremity of the pain, yet with force they thrust on the Lock, and beheld it with joy.</p>
            <p>And in the Hole we had scarce room to put forth our feet, without touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Turks,</hi> whose feet were in the Stocks, &amp; hands in Irons, &amp; necks and feet in Iron bands tyed to the with strong Iron Chains. After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Priests being drunk at their Feast, sent for us to examine us fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and they said they could not believe but <hi>John</hi> was a Preacher; for a Husbandman could not answer so readily. And one of the chief of them told us, they had several Instruments of Cruelty, which they could also let us taste of, and that they could burn men under the Armes, &amp; put hot Iron or Copper plates upon their Breasts, and he also told us that we should be sent down into <hi>Hungaria</hi> to be burned, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I spoke to one of the Priests, and desired of him we might be dealt withal as men or Christians, and might have a little straw or hay to lye upon, for we were worse used then the <hi>Turks;</hi> yea, said he, we prefer them before you. And about that time they proffered us a drink in an urging manner, which it was supposed was made to poison us, &amp; <hi>Iohn</hi> refusing to take it, then said one of the Priests, <hi>Suspectum est nos.</hi> One of the Priests asked me if I had a wife, I, said, I never Knew Woman-kind; he said, the Hereticks had not that grace of Chastity, neither had I any grace from God; the <hi>Turks</hi> had some grace (said he) they were good Souldiers, and somewhat else he said of them. Another Priest asked me how I had lain in the Hole? and how the Iron Shackles pleased me, and threatned how we should be put in the miery Dungeon in the Tower, and called me filthy names in the <hi>Hungarian</hi> Tongue before the people: howbeit, blessed be the Lord, we had slept well in the Shackles upon the Beesoms in a corner, yea better then could be expected, though at the first my Wrist-band pained me much: and when the Priests and others were seeking much to discourage us, I was upon a time sitting musing on a Bench, and thinking, <hi>Lord help us, and what will be the end of this?</hi> and whether shall they have power to murther us here, where few may know of it, being in this place here are no other Sects to be witnesses, as at <hi>Comora</hi> &amp; <hi>Presburg,</hi> &amp; then was my mind turned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, and I was as if I had slept; and on a sudden, it was as if I had seen
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:206905:10"/> a man all cloathed in white, sitting on a milk-white horse, coming riding in post-hast to me wards, as if he were hastning to rescue, then I looked up, and was pretty much Comforted, thinking it was from the Lord to encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage me, lest I should be too much cast down. And the very same day there came tidings from the Earl, that he was displeased at what they had done, as he had told his Barber, to whom he had shewed the Papers which <hi>Iohn</hi> had writ, &amp; hearing of us together, with his perusing the aforesaid Papers, the witness of God was reached in him, which had stirred much in him in the time of his youth, by which he was stirred up to declare against the darkness &amp; deadness of the Brethrens forms before mētioned, among whom he had been educated, neither could he be well satisfied in himself until he came to see, and after some discourse with us, was yet more Convinced, and he told us, how the Earl did judge the Priests had been drunk, which was true, both with rage &amp; wine: then did the streams begin to turn, and some desired our favour, and both the Officer &amp; Priest begun to flatter us with others, who had been high against us, &amp; then they had no more power to put us into the Hole, nor to exercise their Cruelty upon us, as they had done before, which was no small cross to their wills.</p>
            <p>After that there came a spiritual Lord (so called) an <hi>English</hi> man, from <hi>Wien,</hi> &amp; he asked <hi>Iohn</hi> if we came to plant our Religion, saying, the Sects had occasioned much mischief in <hi>England,</hi> but now they would be rooted out; but <hi>John</hi> said, the Love of God can reconcile them again: <hi>A pox a God take that Love,</hi> said he, with other unsavoury words, whereby he shew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed himself to be Carnal indeed, though he was called Spiritual. Another came to us, who was called <hi>Frater Valentine,</hi> &amp; speaking with us concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Bible, he said it had brought many thousands into Hell; and he reading a Paper of <hi>Iohn</hi>'s which he had writ to the Earl and the Council; wherein <hi>John</hi> shewed how he was an <hi>English-</hi>man, and forasmuch as there was no discord betwixt <hi>England</hi> and the Empire, he knew not why an <hi>English-</hi>man coming into any of the Emperours Dominions to visit a sort of people, and to spend his money, should be so used, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but, said the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>said <hi>Frater,</hi> they ought to be beheaded; for if they had done so to <hi>Luther</hi> at first (said he) there had not been so many <hi>Lutherans</hi> or Hereticks at this day: further, he said we were the fore-runners of Antichrist, and this rumour went throughout the Kingdome and elsewhere, That the Anti-Christ was taken, and was at <hi>Nadastie</hi>'s Court: however, soon after it was thought we might have been set at Liberty, but that the Priest did so much incense the Earl against us; and we having writ, according to order,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:206905:10"/> for Certificates, which in due time came to hand from Friends in <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and they were of good service with the Kings Proclamation for setting Friends at liberty, and upon the receipt of them we should have been set at liberty, but the Earl was taken exceeding sick at <hi>Wien,</hi> so that the thing was not then effected.</p>
            <p>In the mean time <hi>Adam Bien</hi> (the Earls Barber) had desired (unknown to us) that we might have the liberty to come forth and lie in his house, the winter being cold, and we in a cold Guard, where the door stood open all day and much of the night, and he proferred his own person in our stead if we should run away, howbeit, we were not free to be so burthensome to him, though he had obtaind the thing, but chused rather to content our selves where they appointed us, that the burthen might come the heavier upon them, that they might be the sooner weary of us: and what storms and assaults we had from the Priests and Souldiers, and others with them, and how they sought to ensnare us, would be too long here to relate; but in the mean time we were often refreshed through <hi>Adam</hi> and his Wives love, together with the sense of the love of God, and friends who were afar off; and our adversaries might have been the worse to us, but that many of them therestood in pretty much awe of <hi>Adam,</hi> who stood in his integrity over them, for he having such daily accesse to the Earl, and knowing most of them at Court guilty of more or less, they did therefore dread him the more; &amp; sometime we did go to his house, &amp; had sometimes opportunities to speak with some of the aforementioned Brethren, who were warned of that sore desolation, which is since come upon many of them, for of nine Families of them there is but one remaining, and the rest were burned with the value of many thousands in them, and above two hundred of the men were slain and taken captive.</p>
            <p>And about that time there was a Gentleman (so called) appointed for to bind me and carry me away, whose waiting man came to me and gave me two big glasses, as if I should have gone with him to have fecht some wine, or something else, but presently I was sensible all was not right of well, for he had a great cudgel in his hand, &amp; that same morning had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven me very bad words; and when I had followed him into the field there came many Sleads (for the snow was so deep that Wagons could not travel) and when the first came at us, the man that had given me the Bottles did cause me to lay them down, and to get up upon one of the Sleads, and he returned back again; &amp; the other who had so much threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned me formerly, came towards me, and then I was very sensible of mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:206905:11"/> intended by them, and then I was troubled for <hi>John</hi> and <hi>Adam,</hi> lest they should have avenged themselves on them through pretending I had been run away, (for they were become full of envy against <hi>Adam</hi> for his love to us,) and I resolved to endeavour to get back to the Town, think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that if they did stop me, it might be the better manifest I was not run away, but when I assay'd so to do, the aforesasd wicked man caught me by the hair in great fury, and shed pretty much of my bloud, &amp; I thought he had quite struck out one of my eyes, and he pulled me down in the snow, and did sorely abuse me, and bound my arms with thongs, as also my feet, and bound me so in the Slead, that I also hung by the arms and feet with my face in the hay, and he and another sat upon me and struck me in the back with a weapon, and bruised me so fore that I could not expect to live long, besides I was almost choaked with my mouth and nose full of bloud so close in the hay, neither knew I to the contrary but they would have murthered me in a short time in that Wood which was close by; but Oh! thought I, that I might but live one quarter of an hour, then paradventure some might passe by and see me, whereby <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>John</hi> might come to know what was become of me; afterwards we came by a Gallows, where I thought they might have executed me, but there we passed by, &amp; people coming that way, they muzzled me with a cloak, and one sat upon me till the people were passed by, howbeit, I hearing their feet in the snow called to them, and desired them to acquaint the aforesaid Barber how I was there, &amp;c. but then did the Souldier beat me sore again, the other having forbid him to suffer me to say any thing, then where we came at night the Irons were put on my feet, and a long big chain tied on high a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout a beam was put about my neck all night; next morning we came to a Village where I would gladly have spoke with one, but they caused me to lie down until we were past both Village &amp; Castle, and so we travelled to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards a place in the Wildernesse as I was informed, and finally we came to a place where they were building a new Cloyster, but the Pryor not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at home, the the other Priests would not take me in without his order, so that night I was put in chains as before, and the next morning was led up to the Castle, and was ordered to be put in a dark hole where no light was, for he that came along with me, bid them blind-fold me, and put me in a deep Dungeon, and to give me but little bread and water, and that none should tell of me, and there being a <hi>Jew,</hi> was forbid on pain of death not to say any thing; and I was soon after put in a hole where there was but little light, and there I was four dayes and four nights in cold frosty
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:206905:11"/> weather, &amp; it was much I was not starved. But after the Pryor wrote home to the Monks, I was sent for, and when they used their Ceremonies, and sprinkled their Infants, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I did not conform to them in their Kneeling, and the like, at which they marvelled, but said not much in my presence; but when I went to my lodging, they said I was a <hi>bad Dog, and a stub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burn Rogue;</hi> and sometime they sent for an armed Souldier to guard me, or rather to affright me. And when I had been there about 12. dayes, the Pryor came home, &amp; it seems he had some order to Rack me for writing Letters at <hi>Puttendorf;</hi> then did the Pryor send for me, and asked me concerning our coming into the Countrey, and to what end, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning some Points of our Religion, to which I answered him accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Truth, but he said that was not enough, we must believe, That the <hi>Pope</hi> was <hi>Christ</hi>'s Vicar, &amp; that He &amp; they had power to bind &amp; loose, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And when we had reasoned a while together, he said, I must have my habitation again in the Castle, and that he would come sometimes by me, &amp; bring the Bible: and afterwards he came up sometimes to see his corn and provision, but had little delight to speak with me, but once he called me where he sate, &amp; told me the Earl had desired him to inform me, that I should not marvel he had sent me thither, for it was not for my sake alone, but for seducing so many soules, and if it could be proved, I was come on such purpose, I should be laid on a heap of wood, meaning I should be Burned. In the mean time I gave my Testimony against their fruits of Covetousness, Pride, Persecution, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and against their weapons, which were not like Christs nor his Apostles; and with this some that stood by were affected, &amp; many things passed betwixt us at that time, which I shall not now rehearse; and afterwards I was told, how he had said to some, he had spoken with many learned men, but never did any answer him as I did. And afterwards I had more Liberty, and more respect shewn me, &amp; the report went, how none that dealt with me could gain at my hand, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And after I was so treacherously taken away, as before mentioned, from <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>John,</hi> the Earl told <hi>Adam</hi> I was run away, and he might see where to find me; he said he could not believe that, but afterwards he got intelligence where I was, and wrote some Lines by the Officer of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle, but he was unwilling to deliver it me, but gave me bad language, say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he had appointed a Hangman to flea off my skin, if I did not turn Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pist: but finally I got a sight of it, &amp; he told me how closely the design of my removal was carried on, insomuch that but three did know of it at first: he also told me how he had longed for an opportunity to send me
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:206905:12"/> bodily necessaries, which he afterwards did, and gave order to give me bread enough on his account; and finally the Earl being sick unto death, <hi>Adam</hi> obtained a promise of him to let us have our liberty; but after he (in whose custodie I was) had received an order to set me free, he kept me six weeks to help the Masons, and promised me to tell me a good message when he returned, if I would be diligent: and afterwards he took me a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>side, and told me, how the Earl would have me informed, how that if I would be a Catholick, I should have good service and preferment; but if not, however he could not detain me, for he had prisoners enough be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sides, but this was concluded, if I were found afterwards in <hi>Hungaria</hi> or <hi>Austria,</hi> I should be Burned, and my Companion the like.</p>
            <p>And before I was brought from thence he did try me many wayes, for he would have me learn to shoot, and hath tyed Match about my fingers, and hath struck me to make me hold the Musquet, but I was like a fool, and they made themselves sport with me, and several times would put Pistols to my hand and bid me shoot; sometimes in seeming earnest, and somesimes to make sport before strangers: afterwards I was examined much about my Religion, &amp; they thinking such a liver would adorn their profes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, did threaten to have my tongue cut out if I would not be a Papist; &amp; afterwards a Priest was sent for to instruct me and convert me, but when he could not prevail, a Tub was made ready, and a Rope put through the cares of it, and I was set in it; and they said I should be let down in a Well thirty six fathom above water, and I knew not but that it might have come to pass; howbeit they drew the Rope but over a Beam to affright me, and I falling out of that, they laid me cross over the saddle of an Ass, &amp; drew me up, and twined it hard about, and let it then go with a whirl, to make my head dizzie, but I was silent, and valued it little; whereat they marvelled, as if I had been past all feeling: and from thence they carryed me to another place, and there they locked my Neck and Feet near toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and my Hands spread abroad &amp; locked in a thing, wherein they tortour the <hi>Turks,</hi> to make them confess of what ability they are, or their friends, thereby to get great Ransome; and some asked if it was painfull, and others said, they committed more sinnes then they did profit thereby.</p>
            <p>And upon another time, I was put i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a great Wheel, which was made for the Well, and they caused the Souldiers to turn it about, that I might tumble to and again in it, which might have done me much hurt, but that I held fast on the side of it; yet however one of my E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ows was in very great danger of being sorely harmed; and afterwards I was much threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned as if they would have Racked me again.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:206905:12"/>
            <p> And about that time I was told by a Secretarie and others, how that the Emperour (by reason of the hot warres that were in the Countrey) had given order to set all the Christian Prisoners at liberty, so that it was thought they could not detain us much longer.</p>
            <p>And about the 4. of the 7. Moneth, 1663. I was carried into the Countrey with the Pryor and a Priest from <hi>Rome</hi> and others; and when we came to the water which parts the two Countreys we parted, and the aforesaid <hi>Adam</hi> had ordered one of them to give me some money for to bear my charge, and he gave me but five <hi>Groshes,</hi> which is about the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue of 10. <hi>d.</hi> After that I came to a place called <hi>Pinkefeld,</hi> where several <hi>Lutherans, Barons</hi> and others came to see me, and many things they asked of me, to which, according to freedome, I answered. And I had a desire to have gotten to <hi>Wien,</hi> but they told me it was impossible for me to pass, that would not take off my Hat; besides, there were abundance of Souldiers that wayes; and one desired me to stay there by him, until I could have an opportunity: afterwards I was directed to go through <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eyermark</hi> to <hi>Gratz</hi> a great City, where there were Merchants from <hi>Nurenberg</hi> at the Fair, and one of them it was thought might be some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what of my opinion, and thither I went, but going in at the Gates was called back, and was not suffered to go in, for they were fearfull of the Enemy, and suspitious of strangers.</p>
            <p>The next day (when I saw I could not meet with the aforesaid Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant) I resolved to travel on my Journey, and to trust the Lord for to care for my sustenance, who had often done it: when as to the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward there was little appearance of Relief: and in my Journey I enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for the privatest wayes, which I found to be most peaceable: howbeit when I came to the West end of <hi>Austria</hi> I was twice stopped, as if I might have been sent from the <hi>Turks,</hi> to spy out and burn Towns, but when I produced my Certificate, I was suffered to pass, but charged not to tarry at their Towns, and after that I avoided coming in Cities and Villages so much as I could, and so got forwards, though not without difficultie: and I have great cause to thank the Lord for his goodnesse, for I did not much want food, but through mercy, got either Bread, or Fruit, or something: for in them Countries they are accustomed to give Travellers and Tradesmen Bread and Lodging in in their Barns: and sometimes I told them how I had been robbed by Souldiers and abused, and then their hearts were moved so much the more with pitty towards me; and I proceeded on my Journey, and through
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:206905:13"/> mercy got about the 2. of the 8. Moneth into some part of the <hi>Palz</hi> in <hi>Germany,</hi> and came through <hi>Heidelberg</hi> and <hi>Manham,</hi> and upon the 7. of the same moneth I arrived at <hi>Crieshiem</hi> among Friends, and being there kindly entertained and abundantly refreshed I tarried there some weeks, waiting to have heard of <hi>John,</hi> or from <hi>Adam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now the last news which I had of <hi>John</hi> was by dear <hi>Adam</hi>'s Letter, which I hope may be come to thy hands before this. Several more passages might be set down, and what we suffered together besides, and I since we were parted; but this for the present may suffice till another opportunity, farewell.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Amsterdam,</hi>
                  <date>
                     <hi>the</hi> 11. <hi>Moneth,</hi> 1663.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Thy dear friend in the light and love of God, <hi>WILLIAM MOORE.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <head>
               <hi>Here followeth an extract out of a Letter from the aforesaid</hi> Adam Bien <hi>to a Friend in</hi> Germany, <hi>bearing date the</hi> 10. <hi>of</hi> 9. <hi>Moneth,</hi> 1663.</head>
            <p>DEar friend, I have received <hi>William Moore</hi>'s Letter, and was glad to hear that he was gotten well among Friends again. <hi>John Philly</hi> departed from hence the 6. of the 7. Moneth, of whom I desire much to hear, whether he be gotten back to you in <hi>Germany</hi> or to <hi>Amsterdam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I wrote to thee about 4, or 5. weeks since, wherein I made mention of the miserable condition these Lands are in, by reason of the extraordinary wars, especially in <hi>Hungaria,</hi> which is expected will extend the next Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer unto this place where I live, where they have not as yet been, but alas, we are daily in jeopardy, either of the <hi>Turks, Tartarians,</hi> or others.</p>
            <p>Upon the other side of the River <hi>Donow</hi> about 48. miles from hence they have burned all before them, for the most part of two hundred miles, so that there is not a house to be found, except some Castles, or strong pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces which the <hi>Turks</hi> have taken and keep for themselves. And many young and old have they slain, and many exposed like beasts to mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serable slavery, and it is expected that it may yet be worse then it hath been; And therefore I do purpose (God willing) to endeavour to get into them parts where thou art the next Summer, if it be free from war there, there to romain for a season: Oh the dreadfulnesse of this war! it is thought the like hath not been known by any one living.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>A. B.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <trailer>THE END.
<pb facs="tcp:206905:13"/>
         </trailer>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>